A Guide to the Staige D. Blackford Papers
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Staige D. Blackford Papers
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
12812-b
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Access to diaries requires written permission from Blackford's daughters through the year 2034.
Acquisition
The collection was given to Special Collections on May 15, 2007 and December 14, 2009 by Mrs. Bettina Blackford and her daughter Sheila Blackford.
Biographical/Historical Information
Staige Davis Blackford (1931-2003) was the son of Lydia Harper Fishburne Blackford and Dr. Staige Davis Blackford (1898-1949), a physician at the University of Virginia and the medical director for the Eighth evacuation team during World War II. Staige was the nephew of Dr. Launcelot Minor Blackford (Uncle Whang 1894-1964) the author of "Mine Eyes Have Seen the Glory." Staige attended Episcopal High School, a private school in Alexandria, Virginia where his grandfather (Launcelot Minor Blackford 1837-1914) had been the headmaster. In 1948 Staige was admitted to the University of Virginia and graduated with a B. A. with honors in 1952. He was awarded a Rhodes scholarship to Queen's College Oxford University from 1952 to 1954 graduating with a B. A. in Modern History. He served in the United States Air Force from 1955 to 1957 as a first Lieutenant. He also worked for the Central Intelligence Agency from 1954 to 1958 specializing in Eastern Europe during the Hungarian Revolution. In 1958 he obtained his first writing job as a reporter for Time, Inc. and married Florence "Bettina" Balding Blackford. In 1960 he was an assistant editor for Collier's Encyclopedia and in 1961 he worked for the Grolier Society Inc. Later that year he became an assistant director in the editorial department for the Louisiana State Press. From 1962 to 1964 he worked at the Southern Regional Council, Inc. In 1964 he accepted a job as a reporter and writer for the Virginian-Pilot in Norfolk Virginia. He was also a speech writer and press secretary for Governor Linwood Holton before moving to Charlottesville in 1973 to work as a special assistant to University of Virginia Presidents Edgar Finley Shannon, and Frank L. Hereford. He was also editor of the Virginia Quarterly Review, a position that he kept until 2003.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of 3,609 items, 13 hollinger boxes, and 5 linear feet and contains the papers of Staige Blackford, which are mostly correspondence with his family, friends and colleagues and newspaper clippings of his articles. Also included are newspaper articles written by his daughter, Linda Blackford. The letters written by Staige Blackford are very descriptive, rich in character, and give information about the University of Virginia, as well as personal details about people, politics and current events in Charlottesville, and around the world. Blackford was a journalist at heart, showing curiosity and writing about all aspects of human life. Correspondents include Vernon E. Jordan, Jr., Peter Batty, Ward Just, Steve Hochman, Sally Bruce McClatchey, Monty and Sally Yudelman, Antonia and Faustina Berenguer, Robert and Jean Bower, Elliot and Kevin Levitas, John Funari, F. Rawdon Dalrymple, Ed Crawford, Ed and Ginger Barber, Barbara and Jean Murphy, Kenneth Winfred Thompson, Alden Read, Junious R. Fishburne, Howard J. and Binky Burnett, Alexander "Sandy" Gilliam, Andrew D. Hart, Helen Dewar (Washington Post correspondent,) Martin and Celia Ochs, Lee Sanford Ainslie, Jr., Fred Hobson, Murray and Sylvia Milner, Thad Holt, Robert Mason (Virginia-Pilot,) Alfred McCormick, A. Hewson Michie, Jr., Ed Elson, Launcelot Minor Blackford, former governor, Linwood Holton, Edgar and Eleanor Shannon, R. W. "Johnny" Apple, Frank Hereford, Larry Sabato, Mary Lee Settle, and William "Widdy" Tazewell. There is brief correspondence with former president William Jefferson Clinton, Doris Kearns Goodwin, Colgate Darden, Robert O'Neil, and John Casteen.
The family correspondence originates with his grandfather Clement "Par" Fishburne who wrote letters to his daughter, (Staige's mother) Lydia Harper Fishburne in 1913. "Par" Fishburne's letters are also extremely descriptive and well written. There are also many letters from Staige's mother and sister which reveal that Staige possessed at a young age, a great talent for using words to describe the passion behind his feelings and ideas. The family correspondence is from 1913 to 1924; 1943 to 1962; and 1984-2003. The general correspondence is from 1945 to 2003 and contains letters to friends, colleagues, charities as well as reference letters.
Besides correspondence and newspaper clippings, the collection contains the personal papers of Staige Blackford such as college admission letters for his daughter, Linda, insurance and financial papers, genealogical information, an autobiography of Staige Davis Blackford, Sr., an original manuscript of Launcelot Minor Blackford's [Mine Eyes Have Seen the Glory,] information about being a Rhodes scholar, speeches written by Staige Blackford including speeches and itineraries for Linwood Holton, a speech by the Reverend John Spong about Vietnam, and United States Army papers.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by topical order and chronologically by date within each folder. The correspondence is grouped into family correspondence, general correspondence and VIP Correspondence.
Contents List
- 1913-1921 Family Correspondence Lydia Harper Fishburne and her father, 32 items (Box-folder 1:1)
  There are mostly letters from Clement "Par" Fishburne to his daughter, Lydia Harper Fishburne (who was the mother of Staige Davis Blackford, Jr. and wife of Dr. Staige Davis Blackford, Sr.
- 1922-1924 Family Correspondence Lydia Harper Fishburne Blackford and her father, 26 items (Box-folder 1:2)
  There are letters from Clement "Par" Fishburne to his daughter Lydia Fishburne
- 1926-1928 Family Correspondence Lydia Harper Fishburne from her father-Par, 21 items (Box-folder 1:3)
- 1924; 1927 Family Correspondence Staige Blackford, Sr. to Lydia Harper Fishburne, 6 items (Box-folder 1:4)
  There are letters from Dr. Staige Davis Blackford to his future wife Lydia Harper Fishburne. They were written while he was practicing medicine at Massachusetts General Hospital and the Mayo Clinic. There is also a poem about [Lydia]
- 1943; 1947-1949 Family Correspondence Staige Davis Blackford Sr. to SDB Jr., 16 items (Box-folder 1:5)
  There are letters from Dr. Blackford to his son (Staige) Included is an autobiography by Staige Davis Blackford, Sr. (in the form of a letter)
- 1944-1947 Family Correspondence, 35 items (Box-folder 1:6)
  There are letters from Staige Blackford to his parents and his sister, Linda. Also included are letters to Staige from his grandfather, Clement "Par" Fishburne. The letters reveal that Staige was homesick and unhappy at Episcopal High School. Staige wrote about the surrender of Germany and his alienation from the celebrations that were taking place. He complained that when Germany surrendered, he was taking a Latin test. Also included is a letter from A. X. Huxton assuring Dr. Blackford that Staige was doing fine work.
- 1948-1949 Family Correspondence, 26 items (Box-folder 1:7)
  There are letters from both of Staige's parents as well as his grandfather
- 1952 Family Correspondence, 16 items (Box-folder 2:1)
  There are letters from Staige's parents, grandmother (Florence Fishburne) and sister while he was studying abroad at Oxford on a Rhodes Scholarship
- 1953 Family Correspondence, 36 items (Box-folder 2:2)
  There are family letters to Staige while he was at Oxford. Included is a letter to Lydia from friends Faustina and Antonio Berenguer in Madrid
- 1954-1955 Family Correspondence, 33 items (Box-folder 2:3)
  There are family letters including letters from Dr. Launcelot. Minor Blackford, ("Uncle Whang") who was a brother of Dr. Staige Davis Blackford. There is also a review of his book, "Mine Eyes Have Seen The Glory" There is also a newspaper clipping about the engagement of Staige's sister, Linda Blackford to Lieutenant Frank Wells
- 1956-1958 Family Correspondence, 28 items (Box-folder 2:4)
  There are family letters including letters from his uncle Dr. Launcelot Minor Blackford ("Uncle Whang") and Frank Wells. L. Minor Blackford expressed his concerns about an inevitable and integrated society with Negroes.
- 1962-1964 Family Correspondence, 6 items (Box-folder 2:5)
  There are letters from Staige to his mother and Uncle L. Minor Blackford. He wrote a description about the South and about his interview for the Southern Regional Council in Atlanta
- n. d. Family Correspondence, 43 items (Box-folder 2:6)
  There are mostly letters to Staige from his mother, father and sister, including a postcard to Lydia
- 1984-1986 Family Correspondence, 3 items (Box-folder 2:7)
  Staige wrote to his daughter, Sheila about her being at camp, and to Mr. and Mrs. Balding
- 1987-1990 Family Correspondence, 15 items (Box-folder 2:8)
  There are letters from Staige to his daughter, Sheila. Also included are papers and reports by Sheila Blackford.
- 1989 Family Correspondence Linda in Paris, 30 items (Box-folder 2:9)
  There are letters from Staige to his daughter Linda while she was studying at the Sorbonne in Paris
- 1990 Family Correspondence, 26 items (Box-folder 2:10)
  There is correspondence between Staige and his daughter Linda while she was working in Paris
- 1991-1993 Family Correspondence with Shelia and Linda, 49 items (Box-folder 2:11)
  There is correspondence of Staige Blackford with his daughters, Linda and Sheila. Staige referred to the students at the University of Virginia as "little darlings"
- 1994 Family Correspondence with daughters, 14 items (Box-folder 3:1)
  Also included is information about the Columbia University Graduate School of Journalism Commencement Exercises in which daughter, Linda was a graduate.
- 1995 Family Correspondence, 48 items (Box-folder 3:2)
  There is correspondence of Staige Blackford with his daughters, Linda and Sheila. Staige mentioned Clinton's scandal: "Monicagate." He also wrote about Governor George Allen who he often referred to as "Boy George." As for news in Charlottesville he wrote about the local debate concerning Charlottesville reverting to a town. He also revealed that there were rumors about John and Lotta Casteen's marriage breaking up. In other University of Virginia news, he mentioned that Terry Holland had been named the new Athletic Director.
- 1996 Family Correspondence with daughters, 36 items (Box-folder 3:3)
  There is correspondence of Staige Blackford with his daughters, Linda and Sheila. Mentioned is the divorce of Jeff and Lisa Jones, an affair of Jeff Jones with the women's assistant basketball coach, the divorce of George and Sandy Welsh, an alleged affair of George Welsh with a woman [in the Carribean,] crimes committed by the UVA athletes, and the disappearance of Alicia Showalter Reynolds on Route 29.
- 1997 Family Correspondence with daughters, 37 items (Box-folder 3:4)
  There is correspondence of Staige Blackford with his daughters, Linda and Sheila. Mentioned is the death of former University of Virginia President Edgar Finley Shannon
- 1998 Family Correspondence with daughters, 30 items (Box-folder 3:5)
  There is correspondence of Staige Blackford with his daughters, Linda and Sheila. Staige wrote about John Casey's new novel "The Half Life of Love" (sic Happiness) which supposedly took place in Charlottesville and the college president might have been based on John Casteen. In other UVA news, Staige wrote that the fraternities and the rushing process might be changed to the second semester; and about a fiasco in which two babies were accidently switched at the hospital. In the political arena he wondered if Doug Wilder was too "thin skinned" to be president of a college. On the national front, he wrote that Vernon E. Jordan was being remembered only as "Clinton's lackey" after all the great work he did for civil rights. He also mentioned Mary Lee Settle's autobiography and that Mary Lee and Ann Beattie had a falling out followed by a rapprochement.
- 1999 Family Correspondence with daughters, 34 items (Box-folder 3:6)
  There is correspondence of Staige Blackford with his daughters, Linda and Sheila. Staige referred to the Board of Visitors as a "group of Neanderthals." According to Staige, the issues that were being hotly discussed at the University were a liberal studies degree in Qatar and the naming of the College at Wise. Staige also made reference to Governor Jim Gilmore as "Big Jim."
- 2000 Family Correspondence with daughters, 36 items (Box-folder 3:7)
  There is correspondence of Staige Blackford with his daughters, Linda and Sheila. He mentioned the presidential election several times in his letters. President John Casteen gave a dinner at Carr's Hill to honor Blackford for his twenty-five years at the Virginia Quarterly Review and the seventy-fifth anniversary of the VQR. Included are photographs from the event. In other news, Staige called Tom Bliley, "Mr. Tobacco" and wrote that it had been revealed that the late John Battle had an affair with his secretary for twenty years.
- 2001-2003 Family Correspondence with daughters, 68 items (Box-folder 3:8)
  Correspondence of Staige Blackford with his daughters, Linda and Sheila (All of the General Correspondence consists of letters to friends, charities and reference letters.)
- 1945-1951 General Correspondence friends, 41 items (Box-folder 3:9)
- 1952 January-August General Correspondence, 23 items (Box-folder 3:10)
- 1952 October-December General Correspondence friends, 31 items (Box-folder 4:1)
  Correspondents include friends such as George Brannock, Ed Granger, Hugo Blankenship, Antonio and Faustina Berenguer, Thorburn Reid III, and Alfred McCormack, Jr. Many of them were colleagues working together on the University newspaper, The Cavalier Daily
- [undated, possibly 1952] General Correspondence, 51 items (Box-folder 4:2)
  Included is a note to Staige mentioning that the Harvard Professor, Edgar F. Shannon was in town and he should meet him
- 1953 General Correspondence friends Oxford, 46 items (Box-folder 4:3)
  There are many letters voicing fear and disgust about the activities of McCarthy. The letters also reveal that the UVA community was upset that Stringfellow Barr signed a petition asking for amnesty for eleven communists convicted under the Smith Act. The students were circulating a petition to remove him from the faculty. Included is a letter from Stringfellow Barr ("Winkie") Verbal attacks by David McCord Wright against Barr are also mentioned. (January 19, 1953)
- 1954-1955 General Correspondence friends, 38 items (Box-folder 4:4)
  There are letters to Staige while he was at Queen's College, and then in the Air Force at San Antonio, Texas and Mobile, Alabama
- 1956-1958 General Correspondence friends, 56 items (Box-folder 4:5)
  There are letters describing the tension between the Supreme Court decision and the southern states regarding desegregation (January 19, 1956). Included is an editorial about desegregation and the South (January 22, 1956) L. Minor Blackford wrote a letter expressing his concerns about desegregation (see Family correspondence Box: 2 Folder: 4)
- 1961-1962 General Correspondence, 10 items (Box-folder 4:6)
  There is correspondence about writing standards for Richard's Encyclopedia.
- 1963-1966 General Correspondence, 106 items (Box-folder 5:1)
  Staige was working as a research director for the Southern Regional Council and wanted to obtain a position at a University Press or a newspaper. He accepted a job with The Virginian-Pilot in Norfolk. Staige also mentioned that his working for the CIA was a mistake because it took him away from his writing. He wrote that his uncle, L. Minor Blackford passed away from complications from emphysema. There is also a letter from the editor of Civil War History criticizing L. Minor Blackford's manuscript "Ride, Boldly, Ride" (about Frank Robertson)
- 1978 General Correspondence Miller Center Advisory Committee, 3 items (Box-folder 5:2)
  There is correspondence regarding the Miller Center Advisory Committee in which Staige Blackford was a member
- 1985 General Correspondence, 40 items (Box-folder 5:3)
  There are mostly letters about visiting and keeping in touch with friends
- 1986 General Correspondence, 53 items (Box-folder 5:4)
  Staige mentioned their trip to Madrid and that Bettina was becoming a professional gardener
- 1987 General Correspondence, 43 items (Box-folder 5:5)
  Correspondents include Martin Shelby Ochs, Alexander "Sandy" Gilliam, Andrew Hart, Julie Just, Helen Dewar, and Ben Bradlee (sent him invitations to formal events)
- 1988 General Correspondence, 101 items (Box-folder 5:6)
  Included with correspondence is a program for the swearing in of James H. Billington as the Thirteenth Librarian of Congress. Correspondents include former Virginia Governor Abner Linwood Holton. Also included is correspondence with Edwin Milton Yoder, Edgar Finley Shannon, Jr., Larry J. Sabato, A. E. Dick Howard regarding an article in Spy magazine about Rhodes Scholars. There is also an article in the Jefferson Journal about Edgar Allan Poe's signature being stolen from the UVA minutes book and the editor asked Staige if L. Minor Blackford had anything to do with the missing clipping. Also included with correspondence are edited notes by Staige on a manuscript by Anne H. Freeman about Hunton and Williams.
- 1989 General Correspondence, 98 items (Box-folder 5:7)
  There is a letter from UVA President Robert O'Neil congratulating Staige's daughter Sheila on her admission to the University of Virginia. Staige expressed criticism of the University of Virginia administration under President O'Neil. Correspondents include A. Linwood Holton, Eleanor Shannon, George Garrett, Ralph Cohen, and Alexander "Sandy" Gilliam, Jr.
- 1990 General Correspondence, 90 items (Box-folder 5:8)
  Included are Staige's editing comments on a manuscript by Steve Hochman and Staige's review of the history of Episcopal High School.
- 1991 January-May General Correspondence, 78 items (Box-folder 6:1)
  Correspondents include The Right Reverend John Spong, Alexander "Sandy" Gilliam, Murray Milner, and Howard J. Burnett. Staige mentioned that the General Assembly had banned the FBI, CIA and U. S. Military from recruiting students from the Law School because the agencies discriminated against gays and lesbians. Staige wrote about the death of Fredson Bowers; and commented on Casteen's first year as president
- 1991 June-December General Correspondence, 80 items (Box-folder 6:2)
  Correspondents include Murray Milner, and Richard Arndt
- 1992 General Correspondence, 88 items (Box-folder 6:3)
  Mentioned are Robert Christopher and Charles McDowell
- 1993 General Correspondence, 67 items (Box-folder 6:4)
- 1995 General Correspondence, 49 items (Box-folder 6:5)
- 1996 General Correspondence, 46 items (Box-folder 6:6)
- 1997 General Correspondence, 45 items (Box-folder 7:1)
- 1998 General Correspondence, 53 items (Box-folder 7:2)
  Staige's daughter, Lynda married Van Meter Pettit. Harold McSween wrote about Bill Clinton and other men he knew that were involved with many women.
- 1999 General Correspondence, 55 items (Box-folder 7:3)
  There is information about the Episcopal High School reunion and the Linwood Holton Governor's Conference.
- 2000-2001 General Correspondence, 75 items (Box-folder 7:4)
  Included with correspondence are a Daily Progress article about George Garrett and a letter from the UVA Seven Society honoring Staige Blackford.
- 2002 General Correspondence, 36 items (Box-folder 7:5)
  Included is a letter from Daniel Jordan congratulating Staige on his impending retirement
- 2003 General Correspondence, 27 items (Box-folder 8:1)
- 1951-2000 VIP Correspondence Clinton and Saul Benjamin, 39 items (Box-folder 8:2)
  Included is a letter from Frank L. Hereford to Staige Blackford. Other letters are from Abner Linwood Holton, R. W. "Johnny" Apple, Robert O'Neil, Edgar F. Shannon, John Casteen, William Jefferson Clinton. There is a handwritten letter from Bill Clinton (signed Bill) thanking Staige Blackford for his "thoughtful letter." There is also an invitation to the Presidential Inaugural Address. There is also a letter from Vernon E. Jordan mentioning that Blackford's suggestion to use quotations from Thomas Jefferson's inaugural speech in the Inaugural Speech of Clinton would be considered. There is a letter of congratulations from Colgate Darden; and a letter from Staige to Governor Douglas Wilder
- n. d. Addresses and invitations, 9 items (Box-folder 8:3)
- 1960-1964. Articles by Staige Blackford, 28 items (Box-folder 8:4)
  "The View from the Twenty-Third Floor;" "Richards En Espanol;" "The Crusades" written for Collier's Encyclopedia; "The Islands at Our Southern Door," written for Richards Topical Encyclopedia; "Letter to a Georgia Gentleman;" "Errol Flynn: A Farewell to Mike," "Letter to A Georgia Gentleman;" biographies of George Canning, John Fitzgerald Kennedy, Richard Nixon, William Pitt, Sir Robert Walpole, Henry John Temple, Henry 1 through Henry VIII, Newton Diehl Baker, Josephus Daniels, and Henry Woodfin Grady. Also included is correspondence relating to the articles.
- 1974; n. d. Articles by Staige Blackford, 20 items (Box-folder 8:5)
  "Dumas Malone A Sage of Mr. Jefferson;" "The University of Virginia: Retrospect & Prospect" written for the American Oxonian; an article about Louisiana; and "The Negro Protest Movement"
- 1990 Articles Stringfellow Barr and Dumas Malone, 36 items (Box-folder 8:6)
  There are notes and articles as well as Staige Blackford's biography of Stringfellow Barr. There is a piece on Spain and experimenters which was probably written by Staige Blackford
- 1974-1982 Articles (Books reviewed by Staige Blackford), 15 items (Box-folder 8:7)
  Staige reviewed "Stringer" by Ward Just; "In the Miro District & Other Stories" by Peter Taylor; "Colgate Darden: Conversations with Guy Fridell;" "Virginia: A History" by Louis D. Rubin, Jr.; "A Family Trust" by Ward Just; "The Great Mutiny and All That" by Molly Kaye; "Women At War," an article about several books; "Jacobs Ladder" by Donald McCaig; "Mark Clark The Last of the Great World War II Commanders" by Marlin Blumenson; "The Big Laugh" by John O'Hara; and "The Negro Revolt" by Louis E. Lomax. Also included is a review of "Earth Works" by Nancy R. Hugo which was probably written by Staige's wife, Bettina Blackford.
- 1966 Newspaper Articles by Staige Blackford, 1 item (Box-folder 8:8)
  A collection of Staige's newspaper articles from a scrapbook
- 1966; n.d. Articles for the newspaper by Staige Blackford, 130 items (Box-folder 8:9)
- 1967 Articles for the newspaper by Staige Blackford, 60 items (Box-folder 9:1)
- 1967 Articles for the newspaper by Staige Blackford, 96 items (Box-folder 9:2)
- 1968 Articles for the newspaper by Staige Blackford, 41 items (Box-folder 9:3)
- 1968 Articles for the newspaper by Staige Blackford, 109 items (Box-folder 9:4)
- 1969 Articles for the newspaper by Staige Blackford, 43 items (Box-folder 9:5)
- 1969 Article drafts (Copy) for the newspaper, 53 items (Box-folder 9:6)
- 2003; n. d. Articles about Staige Blackford, 26 items (Box-folder 9:7)
- n. d. Articles by Linda Blackford Bloor, 12 items (Box-folder 9:8)
- 1943 Autographs book, 1 item (Box-folder 9:9)
- 1913; 1948; 1952; 2003 Certificates and Identification cards, 19 items (Box-folder 10:1)
  Includes The Thirteen Society, Thomas Jefferson Society of Alumni, The Society of the Purple Shadows, Grand Order of Lespedeza (signed by Linwood Holton) Also included is Staige's license and passports